welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where equal hear and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
again all right so uh check-ins I feel
deeply peaceful and with a delicious
focus
welcome to the stoah I am Peter
Lindbergh the Stewart of the stone and
the stone is a place for us to cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge at this moment and
today we're very lucky to have Joe
Brewer how it's gonna work if you're
familiar with the stoa we're gonna do a
question and answer period Joe is gonna
share his thoughts and then we'll have a
chance to source the collective
intelligence so raven yeah we're gonna
hand it over even so we're even continue
to introduce Joe and tell us how it's
gonna work today okay thanks Peter hi
everybody I'm really excited to have Joe
today so Joe is a change strategist
working on behalf of humanity and I'm
gonna bounce it over to him to give him
more full introduction since he's been
working on so many projects recently so
Joe welcome to the stoah Thank You Raven
thank you Peter
it's lovely to be here and as some of
you already know me I'm sort of one of
those anti box people so I don't like to
fit into boxes I've got a lot of you can
relate to that and I think my big focus
areas over the last couple of decades
have been in complexity science and
cultural evolution all directed toward
trying to keep humans from going extinct
which we are foolishly at jeopardy of
doing at the moment and so a lot of what
I will you know talk with you about
today is my experiences and learnings
about the planetary scale ecological
crisis that were in and the global
systems of human cultures that are
driving it and what we might need to do
in order to have you know beautiful
pastures on the other side or maybe
better yet beautiful food forests and
fully intact ecosystems so it's lovely
to be here
great so go ahead and lift us off into
jo-jo worlds I'll be here for you sure
well one thing I want to say and
starting is that a lot of my perspective
across my life and the work that I do
comes from an experience of feeling like
an alien when I was a little kid which
was like three years old on the
playground in preschool wondering why
all the kids were so mean to each other
and and then spending a lot of time in
nature on the farm where I grew up in
Missouri feeling like I didn't belong
and actually kind of hating humans in a
lot of ways like having a chip on my
shoulder in that teenage way and and
stuff and a lot of it being because I'm
a really emotionally sensitive person
but I'm also a pretty good analytic
thinker and so I'm so I start there
because I feel like we're in a crisis
right now that I would call a spiritual
crisis and it's a spiritual crisis
having to do with the very nature of our
existence as human beings and a
spiritual crisis because it's about the
depth and foundations of meaning and
what we consider to be sacred and mostly
about our lack of sense making around
the sacred a lot of people find having
jobs and mythical security as sacred
when they send their kids away and then
never see their kids and I think there's
a lot of confusion like this around they
would much rather have the times with
their kids but what's sacred isn't what
they do and that disconnect is very real
for me a lot of what I see happening in
the world today is based on a
developmental pattern within the Earth's
biosphere that goes back at least three
million years and I want to tell the
story in this way because I think it's
too often we contextualize what's
happening now around superficial and
symptomatic things like there's a global
pandemic and that's the problem which is
like no no no that's a symptom of a
globally interconnected human economy
that's not a cause of the problem and I
think that no that mismatch between true
driving patterns and what's going on is
a real discernment opportunity for us
we can design causation well we can
actually do something about what the
predicaments were in and I go back three
million years in time to tell this story
because something novel happened about
three million years ago in the history
of the Earth's biosphere which is for
the first time at least that we have any
empirical record of some piece of the
Earth's biosphere gained a symbolic
capacity for conceptual thought and that
is that our Homo habilis ancestor is the
stone tool users could look at a rock
and metaphorically project other uses
onto it and then carve and shape it into
those uses and so that's how they
created their hand wielded cutting tools
from from stone so three million years
ago our ancestors evolved the capacity
for conceptual metaphor which is a
foundational piece of human language in
the human mind this began what became
eventually a runaway process of cultural
evolution which is what we're dealing
with in the world today just basically
there emerged from this initial
conceptual capacity of our ancestors the
ability to have an evolutionary process
for human culture now would be either
deeply integrated with its background
ecology or it couldn't become separate
from it and can function in parallel and
this is what a lot of people in cultural
evolution research they call dual
inheritance theory that there's an
inheritance of genetics and the biome
the biological inheritance and there's
also cultural evolutionary inheritance
like we don't develop languages
ourselves they're taught to us by our
culture and a lot of what we get as
humans is being adapted to environments
that are as much human constructed
environments as they are natural
ecological environments and this
actually goes back to those stone tools
three million years ago
um I start here because the problem we
have in the world today is that cultural
evolution in humans but there other
kinds of cultural evolution by the way
like birds with their bird songs and
whales with their whale songs and so on
so cultural evolution is not limited
humans but humans have something that so
far seems to be it the one standout
thing that makes us different
is cultural evolution and the human lime
is cumulative
whereas if not cumulative in any other
species that we have evidence for
cumulative processes by the way
compounding interest and so on they
create exponential change patterns so
cumulative cultural evolution in the
human line makes cultural evolution
potentially exponential and our cultural
evolution has become exponential which
is why we're able to do things like
destabilize the entire planet's climate
system because our culture is now more
powerful than the Earth's climate
regulatory capacities so this thing of
an exponential change in culture is one
of the fundamental drivers of change on
the planet right now that's why we call
this time least geologists do they call
it the Anthropocene we've entered this
unique time in history what I want to
share is some of what I see happening
with the Anthropocene as it relates to
the work of when margolis and James
Lovelock with what they called the Gaia
hypothesis and some of you I'm sure of
familiar with us but for those who
aren't James Lovelock it was one of
those strange polymaths who couldn't
look at a problem unlike anyone else
around him and when he was working for
Caltech on some of their satellite
research projects he was asked a very
specific question question they asked
him was what is the chemical signature
of life on a planet if we were gonna
build a satellite sensor how would we
know if there's life on that planet and
he thought about it for a little while
and said well there would be chemical
processes that would be far from
equilibrium because living systems drive
chemistry far from equilibrium see what
it see things like high concentrations
of oxygen in the atmosphere because
oxygen is highly reactive and would move
toward equilibrium very quickly unless
there's life that's reproducing it and
then they developed a sensor to look at
the oxygen absorption bands including oh
three or a zone that's how they
discovered the ozone layer and they was
on whole or rather I thought the ozone
hole was discovered and so he and when
margaret's developed a framework for the
entire planet to be self-regulatory with
these processes
so the higher the guy hypothesis is that
the Earth's biosphere regulates the
chemistry of the earth to keep life
conducive to life
to paraphrase Jane Janine Benyus as she
says this the entire planet does this
what's different about humans is humans
are able to be compassionate analytic
conscious and self-aware parts of the
planet while it's doing this and so we
are watching ourselves destroy ourselves
which anthropologists and psychologists
talk about this creates a thing called
terror management they need to manage
the terror of knowing their own death
just related to consumer marketing and
lots of fun ways we can discuss in the
Q&A part if people are interested but
well what's really interesting is right
now we're in a time where the Gaia
hypothesis could become the gaia get the
gut like the gaia design pathway where
we as humans could collectively decide
to design a pathway of regulating and
maintaining homeostasis for the earth
and if we did that then we would get to
stick around and if we don't do that
then we may do like ninety-nine point
seven percent of other species and go
extinct and so um so what I see right
now is our interesting opportunity to
recognize the ways that we have taken
things far from equilibrium that are
destructive like pulling a whole bunch
of dead sunlight out of the ground and
pumping it into the biosphere and the
Earth's atmosphere and a span of 200
years seems like that was a pretty dumb
idea and over growing and overshooting
the human population by several billion
people was a bad idea and so now we're
gonna have to deal with the ecological
consequences of planetary overshoot
which are now decades old and we're
initiated before anyone on this call was
born and we have to do with the massive
grieving process of dealing with the
reality of how much suffering we've
already caused and now much is now
guaranteed and built-in for the next 50
to 100 years because if we can hold the
capacity to do that then we can do
something amazing
which is we can bring robust and dynamic
life back to landscapes all across the
planet as the human population corrects
itself ecologically and as the
capitalist extractive economic models
and the dominance territorial conquests
models of Empires and civilizations all
self-terminate because that's what they
all do if you look at the history of
civilizations and empires every single
one of them has collapsed so this one
will - that's guaranteed and so our work
is not to save this civilization but to
keep humans as part of the planet
afterwards and just saying this you can
see this is a tough pill to swallow
there's a lot of grief a lot of trauma
associated with this but I just don't
know waste any time being gentle about
it because it's the year 2020
well I climate action needed to be taken
40 years ago and we didn't the Green
Revolution shouldn't have happened 70
years ago when it did and other things
that we're now dealing with the natural
consequences of and so those of us who
are going to try to do really deep
systemic work now need to have really
good discernment skills for what the
hell's going on and one thing that's
going on is we are centuries to
millennia into a process of planetary
collapse caused by human culture and
we're in the very late stages of it and
it's not in the future it's in the past
and in the present but they only think
the remains is the human civilization
model to collapse as the last part of it
and if we trigger a mass extinction
event then we drive ourselves away - so
with this knowledge in perspective what
I've been doing and a lot of my friends
are doing is learning how to regenerate
landscapes and build regional skill
economies that function as living
systems and that's something that we now
have we fully have the capacity to do
that a lot of the people are attempting
it and there are a lot of great examples
out there in the world of people doing
it right now and last year I was part of
a group called the regenerative
communities network which is a community
of bio regional collaborative where
people are learning how to create
regional scale or territorial scale
economies
for example the Hudson Valley in upstate
New York or the food shed around Boulder
Colorado or the OSA Peninsula in Costa
Rica which has two and a half percent of
the world's biodiversity and so on there
are models of people doing this at very
large scales all over the world and it's
really hard work and it also can't be
done unless we compost the global system
which means the global system has to die
so I'll stop here by summarizing our
paraphrasing the words of Joanna Macy
and just say our work is to be hospice
workers and midwives and we have to do
both at the same time and we have to do
it with the cumulative powers of
cultural evolution by then parrot by
quoting another friend of mine and the
mentor David Sloan Wilson who says we
need to become wise managers of our own
evolutionary process so we have to
understand our evolutionary how it works
what mechanisms and dynamics are and
then we need to employ what the most
wisdom we can using that word on purpose
because most of that wisdom is in our
indigenous cultures and not in our
civilizations although not all of it's
there so that's not romanticize human
systems that are real human systems but
there's a lot to learn from the
indigenous because most of them actually
have been sustainable cultures in the
caste and so I'll stop there because I
think we're gonna have a really rich
conversation from this provocation and
I'm just excited to be here with all of
you so thank you for letting me read for
a few minutes so yeah if things are
coming up for people you can go ahead
and put your question in the chat and I
will call your name and you can ask your
question directly to Joe and I'll just
warm drum up a little bit here so
initially I would just like to ask you
about the role of religion in all of
this I think in the secular world we
seem to we struggle with the idea of
becoming religious even there's even an
idea around the stove of like the
religion of no religion you know kind of
still grappling with this idea of
religion what do you what do you think
about
and what role does religion have to play
in in earth regeneration there's a
really great book by a guy named Edward
goldsmith he's a cross cultural
anthropologist and his book is called
the stable society what he observed was
that every stable society translation
every sustainable culture has Pro future
social norms embodied through religious
practices that personify nature and
treated as sacred so the river is not an
object the river as a person the
mountain is not an object the mountain
is a person the bear is not an object
the bear is a person and their kinship
relationships that honor you the other
the other being as sacred so if you look
just with empirical evidence of human
culture this has been an essential
element of sustainability so this
indigenous aspect of spirituality is
essential now the religion plays another
important role that is beyond this and
I'll use the example of Bali and their
Sue box so sue box are basically nested
areas of water and land management for
terraced gardens where the terraced
gardens are mostly growing rice and the
thing to know about the cereal box in
Bali is that they're structured as
nested fractals around a series of or a
network of different water temples and
these water temples have a religion of
treating each piece of land in each of
the waterways as having its own spirit
or its own god or goddess and when
people pay homage to the gods or the
goddesses they are actually reporting
and accounting the information they need
for collectively and management and so
that they have managed their water
system for more than 1,000 years at high
levels of productivity without
destroying the water or the land
availability because of the cooperation
enabled by their religion so the big
lesson for us from religion is that it
is a way of recognizing how to bring
cultural evolution to have cooperation
occur at higher levels and to be
functional at those higher levels you
can get a really strong group
election patterns and that's a really
key thing about religions so they don't
necessarily need to be structured as
religions to do that but that's an
essential piece of villages so I'm so
those are two answers to pieces that
question great thank you and then I'm
gonna ask a question on behalf of
Benjamin as far as renewable materials
for sustaining civilizations what makes
sense to cultivate what makes sense to
abandon well one thing we need to look
at is the self renewing patterns of the
earth that are at the planetary scale
and this will start to give us some
answers one of the most important
measures we need to be aware of is
called net primary production which is
if you look at the entire planet's
surface and add up all of the
photosynthesis that's happening then
you'll get this measure of net primary
production primary production as plant
biomass forming from photosynthesis and
there are a lot of ecological reasons
why that is a foundational capacity for
any ecosystem the productivity of the
plants is one of the Leben limiting
factors of what the ecosystems can do so
if we look at things like solar panels
or wind turbines which have a lot of
non-renewable things in them and
currently they require a lot of fossil
fuels to make home and they're no it
nothing close to a solution in a
systemic way for these reasons there's
another thing is we need to understand
the resilience of food webs and
ecosystems to see that if we destroy in
touch forests and replace them with wind
turbines and collapse biodiversity
eventually we're going to trigger an
extinction event and go away even though
we quote-unquote solved our energy needs
the reason being that we converted too
much of the land surface into machines
primarily for human uses and that
anthropocentrism was actually the
problem so so many look at materials
that have different limits we need to
look at them in these two ways one is
what are their total capacities like how
much net primary
there and then the other is what are
their distributive qualities that allow
them to be resilient so it's net primary
production or solar energy being turned
into life is put into a brittle
ecosystem very small biodiversity and
primarily humans were you know
domesticated animals for humans or
whatever else then you have a fragile
system that can collapse and so the
question is answered both in the amount
of the materials and their networking
relationships and it's together that we
see whether or not they're truly
renewable so so this is important for
metal or where you get the metal or by
cutting down mountains and blowing them
up with fossil fuels and destroying
biodiversity and other things like this
so so it's a really interesting thing to
flip this conversation from how much of
the material is there to instead what
are the resilience patterns of network
connectivity and what are the disruption
tolerances to those networks so it's not
how much ore is available it's how much
more can we take without destroying
these ecosystems and most people don't
contextualize the question in this way
so it becomes a raw number and that's a
really dangerous thing to do
excellent thank you maybe gray would you
like to ask your question okay thank you
um I hear from you um an emphasis on the
grief that there is to feel over what
has already sort of occurred before we
can really move forward with what has to
be done next I'm wondering if you could
talk a bit about how we can really
appreciate the value of that work and
prioritize it yeah I have a specific
perspective on this that I hope is
helpful I mean it comes in two parts one
part is how ecological secession works
which is that new life emerges by
consuming the bodies of the dead so we
have to have a way of celebrating death
and have a healthy relationship to death
no no I'll just let that stand it's sort
of like a philosophical perspective
because there's a lot to say about it
the other part that's much more
practical and tangible is that our
greatest capacity as human beings is our
capacity to have empathy and then from
the empathy to have nuance and if we're
going to go into a degraded landscape
like where I'm living right now in
Colombia we're in a tropical dry forest
98% deforested so a lot of people would
look at this as a dead landscape but if
you're a sensitive person you'll pay
attention to the patterns and if you're
a sensitive person you'll notice where
life still exists but if you're
sensitive person you will also be hurt
by harm caused to life and so the grief
that you have that gets converted into
trauma is the numbing of that
sensitivity and if that sensitivity is
numb then you can't do permaculture you
can't feel into and pay attention to the
patterns and then help them grow so you
have to get to a stage of grieving to
become sensitive again and this is
deeply deeply pragmatic and so on so I
see this as one of the really essential
things and there's also a part relating
that's about letting go of control like
we're in their community that's trying
to do permaculture led by children and
we're trying to build a regional skill
regenerative power
around children or set of patterns
around children to go out like we did
this morning when we were digging water
retention like little ponds and starting
to build swales with our three-year-old
daughter playing with one of the tick
axes and digging in a hole with us we
need to actually listen to the patterns
of the children and again that's about
about celebrating the joy of the future
instead of being filled with anguish
about the future those children are
going to inherit and so the grieving
gets in the way of all these processes
it overwhelms our perception systems
that we need to do the work well so I
think that's a really important piece of
this a lot of other pieces too but but
I'll just hold that one for the sake of
the conversation but I think it's super
important wonderful Darrell what do you
like to ask you a question yes we've
seen blockchain do a lot of wild things
with economies and probably not the most
positive things but I do wonder do you
see a role for blockchain to support the
creation of regenerative economies yeah
so I'll tell this story and it's sort of
roundabout way but you'll see its
importance in a moment because this is
related to blockchain and hollow chain
and all the related body of technology
work that people are doing and that is
that a study just came out published in
Nature by a group of researchers at the
Santa Fe Institute it was published last
week so it's very new and what they were
do what they did is they looked at the
sea shot world history databank which is
an aggregation of archaeological and
anthropological work so they could do
statistical analysis on human societies
they looked at the patterns of
development for 291 political systems
most of which collapsed and they noticed
that there were two developmental stages
for all of these societies and this
relates to your question the first one
is once they established agriculture
because they were looking at kind of
city-state development and beyond once
they established agriculture the growth
in population drove the growth pattern
and complexity pattern for the culture
and this is uniform for all 291
seiyya tease until they reached a
complexity information threshold where
the complexity of their society became
so great that if they did not invent
tools for managing information they very
quickly collapsed whereas the second
phase of development for a subset of
these societies was all the ones that
created things like accounting systems
money and other things I could use
information to manage complexity and
then from there you saw a diversity of
further development where each polity
developed differently but it was their
capacity for processing information that
was important now yeah I think Darrell
you probably know the connection but
I'll make it really explicit what things
like blockchain are doing for us is
they're giving us a multivariable
accounting system that allows us to
track multiple parameters at the same
time so we can have very complex
information about very complex patterns
and this is going to be really important
when we're regenerating it regenerating
ecosystems and when we're building human
economies that are integrating with them
so one of the big challenges that's
happening in the world right now around
regeneration is how to do valuation and
risk management for investments for
regenerative projects you know people
from the investment world just don't
know how to value things like
biodiversity and so what like the region
network is trying to build some of these
intermediate tools or they can use
things like blockchain to track value
creation across the diversity of
variables so that you can actually
measure the value of it which allows
people to manage risk for investment so
this is one way that complexity can be
managed that these tools are really
important for and I see a lot of the
decentralization that is about to
emerged that allows scalability is gonna
come from this blockchain in related
technology space but I see it as really
important for managing complexity and
for discerning reality in evolutionary
environments so I hope that answers the
question well enough I think it's very
important
thank you Paul
hmm would you like to ask your question
I cannot I can ask for it
sorry about that okay yeah I couldn't
know I'm you myself sorry about that
yeah great stuff really enjoy this um
but you know and perhaps because I'm
older and I've experienced much more in
life um we have an issue that needs to
be addressed as well humans for
centuries famila onion have gone to war
against each other
or resources mostly it's you know that
tribe has what I want so we'll go and
take it
chimpanzees do the same thing they'd go
to war for resources no matter how how
in touch with nature they are in what
kind of religions they have that they
are they respect nature and so forth
they still behave rather poorly against
each other when when they desire
another's resources how do we um
overcome this because it's it's part of
for these sociopathology that I'm humans
are I blessed with four cursed with we
have this inside of us overcome yeah
this is a fantastic question and one way
to think about it is to take population
density and and increase the number
until the threshold is reached and
you'll notice that a scarcity pattern
will set in this is true with what
chimpanzees for example they do this and
a lot of animals do it humans do it too
so the way we need to address this is to
employ a specific insight that comes
from a study of evolutionary transitions
and an evolutionary transition is when
two previously separate living organisms
or two or more that becomes a biotic
start to develop enough functional
integration that they become
interdependent and can no longer survive
on their own the famous example of this
is mitochondria used to be a bacteria
I was eaten by another bacteria sort of
lived in it's and it's you know
ancestral stomach but eventually they
became so codependent with each other
an evolutionary transition occurred and
we went from prokaryotic cells to
eukaryotic cells or cells without
organelles inside them to cells with
organelles inside them and this
transition to functional interdependence
is the key so the way I see this working
for humans is we need to create bio
regional economies that are organized
around functions of landscapes
it's like watersheds and mountain ranges
and coastal estuaries and things like
this and that we need to create trade
and exchange between bioregions that
lead to
yes symbiogenesis is the name for this
think you rose from the great work of
Lynn Margulis that this is this
functional interdependence comes by
intentionally designing for
interdependence this is actually
something that globalized economy has
done really well what Brian Barber
called the McDonald's effect just that
no two countries ever McDonald's go to
war and that's because they're
economically interdependent and I think
that insight is really important for
regenerative economies do you create a
great regenerative the economy in one
place all you are is a potential
invasion point for someone else who
hasn't integrated with you in the future
now I can say this is oh it's simple
well I can say it any may sound like
it's doable and not that hard
this is gonna be really really hard to
do but those of us who are trying to
build a planetary regeneration pathway
need to know how to build this
interdependence from one bio region to
another until they form a mesh network
across the entire planet and we have to
do this as we deal with overpopulation
and scarcity of resources and I'll share
another study that was one of those
statistical overview studies that is
really damn depressing but we need to
hold it in mind as there was a study
using what's called the H RAF a database
the human relation area files just
hosted at Yale and it's a collection of
anthropological and archaeological
research for different cultures to
compare them with each other and what
they did is they create a parameter
measuring existential risk so like in
each place where there are a lot of
invasions from other cultures where
there a lot of volcanoes
earthquakes where is there a lot of
extreme weather Nikola bulk measure of
existential risk and then what they did
is they looked across history at all
human cultures that were in the database
and found that if there's high
existential risk it naturally selects
culturally for strong men dictatorships
and fundamentalist religion
what does climate change do it creates
widespread existential risk everyone on
earth and so we are creating exactly the
conditions for strong man governments
and fundamentalist religion in this time
when we need to create interdependent
bioregional economies so so easy to hold
the paradox of this in mind that we're
actually entering in one of the worst
environments as it relates to
existential risk to create the
conditions for cooperation and
interdependence but exactly for that
reason that we have to focus on
cooperation and interdependence and so I
think one of the keys is to ask the very
question you asked Paul which is you
know this is a real pattern what do we
do about it and we have to ask it and
every one of our design questions and
every project were working on or else
we'll sit in a little kumbaya place
until someone invades and kills us and
so we just need to be aware of this it's
it's an extremely important question and
discussion thank you thank you for
asking
great thank you and I'm gonna ask a
question on behalf of Evelyn does
beginning the work of building a
foundation for a new kind of society
required defection from this one how can
we foster coordination in the ruins of
this society yeah one of our biggest
problems is what I call developmental
infringement which is that as structures
form they become limiting factors for a
few structures to form it's a
fundamental piece of how patterns work
and one of our problems now is that our
globalized civilization system or set of
systems are all deeply entrenched and so
there's the need to go far enough away
from them that you can innovate without
being pulled into their constraints and
there's also a need to have a buffer
protection against collapse patterns one
of the measures of this flirting he was
really interesting is when I learned
from Jordan Greenhalgh when I was on a
call with him last year I'm guessing a
lot of you know who he is but he is part
of a group looking at existential risk
and the group that he's a part of
developed a specific measure it was
really interesting they observed that
there's a sweet spot of living between
three and five hours away from an
international airport where you're close
enough to benefit from the innovation of
a city but far enough away to be
buffered from its central connectivity
and I'm an example of this I'm in body
charter Columbia it's four hours to the
nearest airport and there have been zero
cases of kovat here the big problem is
that they shut down all transport in and
out of the town and 80% of the economy
is tourism
so they immediately killed the town's
economy but no one's dying from covered
so you can see that were in this place
we're in this town of about 5,000 people
there are at least a couple hundred who
have university degrees have worked in
bogota who have lived in other cities
but they came here because it's this
beautiful peaceful place in the
mountains so we have captured or we've
harnessed the creative and innovative
potential of the city while buffering
and protecting ourselves against
collapse patterns and so I think this is
an interesting element of how evolution
works for us another story I want to
briefly tell is something from the work
of Ernst Mayr for those you don't know
him Ernst Mayr is one of the most
important biologists of the 20th century
and it was well known in the field of
biology but not necessarily outside of
it and he wrote an essay that I read a
few years ago about the evolution of
novelty how does something truly new
emerge through evolution and he told the
story of lungs for amphibians because
you know all of us land-dwellers
emerge from fish or promotion dwellers
so we had to go from gills to lungs it
turns out the way that lungs evolved was
that there was a parallel redundant
system the fish could breathe with their
gills so their life supports were
there was strong natural selection
against changing gills
small tweaks to the gills kill the
organism so don't mess with that but
they had a lot of fish now these swim
bladders that sort of fun like they
function like really lousy lungs and
they could function like really lousy
lungs for lots of generations gradually
becoming more and more like lungs so the
relaxing of evolutionary pressure to
select to select against change with
parallel evolution is how novelty
emerges so this is the role of these
small towns these permaculture projects
yeah slack in the system exactly this is
slack with in the evolutionary processes
itself and the way we do this is by
creating a structural decoupling and
buffering to protect the novel systems
so there's not a lot of debt tying them
down there's not a lot of short-term
feedbacks that require them to respond
to the other system there's not a lot of
leveraging from this old system that
will take the new system down with it if
something goes wrong with the old system
and there's a lot of room for creativity
and failure which is extremely important
and all of us who do innovation work
know how important the ability to fail
is so that I think this perspective on
parallel evolution with redundancy and
structural separation is really key to
answering this question but I just want
to say thank you Bart
would you like to ask your question
[Music]
thanks Joe so I can't I'm hearing a lot
of low tech solutions for the
environmental issues which makes total
sense and feel really good I'm just I'm
wondering if you see any kind of
high-tech solutions out there for
environmental issues that are viable you
know you mentioned wind and solar
really not being good long-term
solutions for energy issues I come from
I work in the building trades and I
really kind of work in the low low tech
area of energy efficiency you know
better insulation better materials
better air tightness etc in the kind of
greater environmental issues that you're
looking at more globally is there any
high tech kind of reason for hope I
think there are high tech elements and
it's important to separate them from the
high tech world to see their value one
of them is biomimicry and material
science but then to step back away from
material science and and say well what
happens when you have that much
sophistication and biomimicry like when
you're looking at the molecular level of
you know energy diffusion processes or
whatever other things that it's that
capacity or creativity that's really
powerful and when we tried to green our
supply change to remove toxins from the
manufacturing materials and and other
things related to you know distributed
manufacturing I think there are two
aspects of high tech one is the material
science itself and the other one is the
information ecology the distribution of
information processes so think of like a
million hacker makers spaces around the
world with some kind of aggregate
learning capacity across them could be
extremely high tech even though a lot of
the things they actually do are like you
know taking a hammer and hang it on a
piece of metal so it's a mix it's a real
mix the other one which I saw named into
the chat with drones is using remote
sensing information processing and
specifically one of the biggest
revolutions in human history which is
what computer science really did
computer science gave us the ability to
run simulations of reality and explore
reality using simulations we could do
computational modeling and computational
modeling is why we have general
circulation models there the u.s. clinic
so like computational modeling is why
of the field of the science of ecology
so it's hugely important a very advanced
science for computational modeling
scientific visualization and information
processing which includes satellite
remote sensing and other kinds of remote
sensing and the day to day analytics
data storage data transfer and data
processing tools so there's a huge room
for this because if we want to create
homeostasis for the planet we need to
create something that functions like
this the cerebellum does in our brain
and what the corpus callosum does in our
brain the corpus callosum is the place
where your left and right hemispheres
connect we've done this with in the
neocortex or within the whole cortex
actually and it's the most dense range
of connections because that's where all
the global coherence of your brain comes
about because of those deep connectivity
in that part of your brain so if we're
gonna create a corpus callosum for the
planet then we're gonna do a lot of
high-tech information like information
communication technology design and the
blockchain and those other pieces that
are I would say are subsets of that so
really high tech information systems and
really high tech material science
systems and I would say really high tech
information creation systems and I call
it that way to be general because or
it's innate intelligence creation
systems because intelligence doesn't
know what it's gonna create yet which is
why it's sort of a catch-all word we
need ways of continuing to learn to get
better at learning and looking at what
we've done with material science like
taking a you know a transmission
electron microscope which is a piece for
the ants technology and looking at how
the surface of the eye for a fee fly
works and then creating a material for
high-altitude mountaineering this is a
pretty freakin awesome thing and so I
think that kind of high tech is gonna be
it's gonna remain important especially
during the transition when we have such
scarce resources you know during this
next 50 years it's going to be extremely
important and it may become more
low-tech after that and that's okay
but I can't say for sure one way the
other
no great thank you so I'm gonna ask
another question on behalf of Benjamin
do you see any role for artists in this
movement all of us are artists yes yes
absolutely let's talk about a couple of
kinds of art one kind of art that I
think is really important and you really
want to dig into this go look at the
writings of Peter Berg as he was writing
about bio regionalism at the planet drum
foundation is that a lot of bioregional
cultures or Arts and Crafts cultures if
you look on my wall right over here this
is his mud packed housing as earthen
construction an artist built that you
look at that roof where someone has
taken Canas which is a real relative of
sugar cane and they've treated it and
process it that's a woodworker that's
craftsmanship that's an artist we have
stone workers we have pottery we have
basket weavers because I'm in Andes
they're all these kind of ancestral
indigenous craft skills a lot of
bioregional economics is about craft
skills and you develop crafts with arts
and crafts mindsets so just in that way
you can see we're building an economy on
arts and crafts it's it's that
foundational another way that arts and
crafts that or that art plays a role and
I really found in a really important way
is in meaning-making
which has to do with songs and in poetry
and how they can give us give us social
context to express our feelings when
we're not otherwise able to express them
to bring us together in ceremonial and
ritualistic ways to form human bonds to
commiserate something being well done
which gets not the craftsmanship of
fermentation like having beer and wine
both of which are fermented beverages
that actually having parties and
festivals and doing theater and using
them to tell our stories and to use them
as like cultural seed banks you know
think of William Shakespeare as a
cultural sink seedbank of the 17th
century in the 16th century
we have those plays to reenact the
stories of those people at that time it
was the screenwriters who did
and so so you can see various ways that
artists can play roles in all of this
and one of the more important ways that
they can help that's really important
right now is to help us dream bigger and
to dream more realistically because
right now we have entirely dystopian
futures and all of our superhero movies
it's catastrophic what's happening with
the film industry
just how much regurgitated shit is
coming out of the film industry even
though we have some of some of the best
educated and best trained storytellers
that history has because so many people
now to do a well and so we need to
direct our storytelling toward emotional
processing of grief as maybe now we're
talking about a few minutes ago and so
that we can imagine different futures
you know what I am in buddy Choi
everyone's worried about water because
we're running out of water here but
almost no one knows what to do about it
they don't how to imagine it they don't
know that you know building ponds and
planting trees will bring water back
they can't imagine it they don't know
how so our storytellers can help them
imagine better and I think that's a
really important thing to do right now
so there's a couple couple of pieces so
arts very important ok thank you and I
want to get a question into right now so
you're talking about overpopulation so
I'm wondering about the decision to
become a parent how do you view
parenting how do you view educating of
children whenever I found that for a
little bit for me yeah yeah I just gave
a webinar on parenting for our three
generation last week and we have a three
and a half year old daughter and the way
that I am addressed this question in the
webinar I gave was I said the answer to
the question should we how should you
have children or should anyone have
children the answer is an ethical
question the ethical question is or
humans good for the planet or bad for
the planet and notice that's based in
belief and not based in reality because
some humans are good for the planet and
some humans are very obviously bad for
the planet so it's not it's not simply
one or the other it's
what do you believe and then what do you
choose to enact and so what I feel in a
time of overpopulation is that anyone
who chooses to have children needs to be
responsible for raising their children
to be net positive for the planet - the
best thing that they can and that's just
a natural requirement so they're minutes
time if they're aware of what's going on
they're either being selfish for doing
it or they're being reckless because
they're placing their child in danger
because the next you know few decades
are going to be pretty difficult and so
what I think of in terms of parenting
and the the regenerative practices
related to parenting is some of us
really simple let kids play outdoors
give them unstructured time teach them
arts and crafts teach them social and
emotional skills you know like a lot of
it's pretty basic but then there are
specific things that like my wife and I
made the decision that we wanted our
daughter to feel like it's completely
normal everyone around her regenerates
landscapes so we need to live in a place
where that's happening and we need to
help that happen so our daughter is 3
and a half and she's learning about
water retention reforestation
identifying native plants and other
things like this because that's just
what people do and it's normative we
want it to be her social one I think
that regenerative parenting is around
building these these normative
expectations the other thing that we
need to do as parents is cultivate
really powerful complexity management
skills like think of kids that do Improv
Theater or anyone who does in front
Peter where it learns mindfulness
meditation practices they need to have a
flexibility to adapt and update their
thinking they need to have a high
tolerance for uncertainty and they need
to work really well in teams and so this
is going to be really important for
parenting and then a third thing that I
think is really important is parents
themselves need to become students which
is we need to learn how to be a
regenerative with our children
oftentimes led by our children we find
ways for our children to get education
that then we participate in and we learn
to be
one of the things that needs to happen
is we need to undo a great mistake the
great mistake was this pattern of
civilization has destroyed and killed
most indigenous cultures on earth so
every human being alive today is the
descendant of indigenous people but most
of us don't remember it most of us at
our ancestral lines cut off and so our
descendants when we become ancestors we
need to begin the process of becoming
indigenous for and for our descendants
to be the future indigenous and so as
our children get these learning
opportunities we get to practice being
indigenous and so means we participate
in these practices as adults as our
children are doing it and most of us
don't know how to do it so we learn
right beside them which by the way I can
attest it's my daughter and my wife or a
play or in the other room making a
natural play dough with our neighbor how
much fun it is to learn to do
regenerative with your children so this
is actually a pretty awesome waste but
those are a couple of the key pieces of
it really important parenting is a big
part of this thank you and then I want
to get in this last question from Raya
would you like to ask your question
sure thanks Raven and Thank You Jo I am
just so resonant with how much emphasis
you have on indigenous cultures because
when you start to study the stories and
the mythology it's so obvious like their
connection to the earth and how they
celebrated it and respected it and I
think as a global society we've them
from the majority we've really lost
touch to that and so my question is like
how do we guide or inspire the human
race back to that indigenous inspired
connection to the earth and do you
believe that we have the actual capacity
as a global society to live harmoniously
and synergistically with the planet we
don't have the global society what we do
as planetary system Anna teri citizens
of bioregional societies as all
indigenous cultures are bioregional and
so I think that that's the key because
we can still be planetary and
awareness but we have to be regional you
know with our own landscapes I have some
friends that are doing really awesome
work it's Cassandra Ferreira Zoe Wilde
and Jennifer monkey who are three women
that each worth work with different
wisdom traditions and all of them are
working with land regeneration and
cooperatively and ownership and they
have been developing something that they
call the sacred contract which is a bit
confusing in a way because the sacred
contract is actually a relationship you
cultivate over time more than
specifically a contract but the idea is
how to help people begin to become
indigenous by feeling a sacred
connection to their land so if you have
someone who has a piece of land there
are simple things like find the oldest
tree on your land and then here's a
simple ceremony and from that ceremony
start to feel how precious that tree is
and so there are activities like this
and that's just a nice concrete example
or if you live in a place where
indigenous people still exist they're
First Nations people invite them onto
the land and do a reclamation process
ask for their blessing for regenerating
the land ask for their wisdom and their
guidance and and show your humility as
someone from the colonizer culture which
will give us access to trust based
relationships to build a sacred
relationship to the land and so
Cassandra Zoe and Jennifer have been
developing this as a way of helping
people make land purchasing decisions so
if someone wants to buy land they might
put a deed restriction they might put it
into a Community Land Trust they might
create an eco village or an intentional
community but if they don't go through
this process of making the land sacred
then they don't know how to legally
protect the land and they're not
cultivating the cultural capacity to
protect the land and so on so I think
this is how we do it it is by forming
intimate relationships body-based
relationships with the land that we're
on and when we do that it's amazing how
how apt how capable humans are feeling
the sacred and so
so even those of us who have been like
PTSD for decades will be surprised by
the healing power of touching the oldest
tree on their land and weeping that the
tree is not old enough maybe the oldest
tree is 20 years old and just think like
how painful that is
and so like so that opening up is I
think is how we do it through these very
simple practices and we do it as locally
as possible so that you can walk back to
that place anytime and reestablish the
connection great that was beautiful
thank you Joe where where ways we can
reach you or what are things how can we
get involved in projects that you're
doing and stuff like that well I mean
I'm actually very intentionally trying
to remove psychological shadow patterns
from my life because I have a long
history of being like a flame that
attracts narcissistic moths and and so
I'm not trying to promote my work what
I'm trying to do is promote Gaia's work
as much as I can and there is a project
I'm involved in what that has come into
being through this mind set which is we
have a study group called Earth
regenerators which is hosted on a mobile
app called mighty networks and so it's a
really powerful app for hosting online
courses but I'm giving a three version
it's in the spirit of the gift economy
there are three generators now I was
like 1300 members and it's only four and
a half months old I was just becoming
something pretty cool and its structure
is around what I want people to be a
part of which is how do we learn how to
see the design pathway for regenerating
the entire planet by regenerating the
landscapes that make our own lives
possible where does our water come from
where does our food come from where do
all of our building materials come from
etc how do we connect to our land and
then how can we change those
relationships in a coordinated and
nested fashion so that it scales up to
planetary health and so the earth
regenerators study group is a place of
learning for us to all figure that out
together and everyone is invited
but um what I care about even more than
that is go find that old tree on your
land
you know like I'm do the regenerative
work in yourself and don't worry about
doing it with me unless you're really
drawn to something that yes because
you're specifically meeting that happens
to be in the space that I'm holding
because too many egos are get in the way
of this work right now
okay I'll just need to get to it but I
just feel really honored and blessed to
be a conduit for this conversation and
this time when we all need to be doing
this work great thank you so much Joe
thank you so much for being here it's
really a pleasure and with that I'll
pass it over to Peter and we'll do
closing statements yeah I'll make some
announcements in a moment I just wanna
throw some appreciation at Joe's way
Jason Schneider who's also here we were
talking last night about you know the
people who are talking about this
meta-crisis and some of the energy that
surrounds it is like an energy of shame
you know you're not being good enough
and we're not addressing this the right
way and listening to you talk like is
evident you know your stuff it is
evident that you're not shy about
talking real but I feel it's coming from
a place that's like deep care and love
and it is just this is fucking beautiful
so thank you for coming today men and
visiting they're stolen
we'd love to have you back and you know
we talked about a lot of intense stuff
here so we're gonna have a sense making
session afterwards it's gonna be run by
Raven and I have to go but she will take
care of that
and I'll just do some announcements for
upcoming sessions at the stoah we have a
Pat Ryan tonight at the dark stoah
that's at 8 p.m.
8:30 p.m. Eastern Time Nancy Strickler
the co-founder of Kickstarter he's
coming in on Monday June 1st 4:00 p.m.
Eastern Time on bento ISM guy to self
coherences and Daniel Thornton's welcome
back party at the six thing day on
Monday June 1st 6:30 p.m. Eastern Time
he's going to talk about his experience
of being away for 75 days I believe a
meditation South meets quite a treat
that being said in Raymond you want to
plug your own Socratic speed-dating
sure so yeah later on today I'll be
hosting a social mixer event we'll be
playing a game called a Scholl which is
a social boundary breaking game so
invite all of you to come if you want to
get some your social boundaries broken a
little bit and meet some people here at
the stoah so yeah and those are really
fun that's 7 p.m. Eastern time today and
the Stowe is based off the gift economy
as we view it as a gift for us to use
freely and this time of need if you're
inspired to provide a gift to the store
you just go to the web page and check
out the gift economy at the bottom of
the page all right thanks everyone thank
you